Beyond darkness... beyond desolation... lies the greatest danger of all.
The Hobbit: The Desolation of Smaug is a fantasy,
adventure, action film directed by Peter Jackson.
The Dwarves, Bilbo and Gandalf have successfully escaped the
Misty Mountains, and Bilbo has gained the One Ring.
They all continue their journey to get their gold back from the Dragon, Smaug.
Gandalf the Grey, played by Ian McKellen.
Bilbo Baggins, played by Martin Freeman.
Thorin Oakenshield, played by Richard Armitage.
Smaug / Sauron, played by Benedict Cumberbatch.
Legolas, played by Orlando Bloom.
Tauriel, played by Evangeline Lilly.
The Hobbit: The Desolation of Smaug is a 2013 epic high fantasy adventure film directed by Peter Jackson from a screenplay
by Fran Walsh, Philippa Boyens, Jackson, and Guillermo del Toro, based on the 1937 novel The Hobbit by J.
The sequel to 2012's The Hobbit: An Unexpected Journey, the film is the second instalment in The
Hobbit trilogy, acting as a prequel to Jackson's The Lord of the Rings trilogy.
The film follows Bilbo Baggins as he continues to accompany Thorin Oakenshield and his
fellow dwarves on a quest to reclaim the Lonely Mountain from the dragon Smaug.
Pursuing them are the vengeful orcs Azog the Defiler and his son Bolg, while Gandalf the Grey
investigates the return of a long-forgotten evil force in the ruins of Dol Guldur.
The ensemble cast includes Ian McKellen, Martin Freeman, Richard Armitage, Benedict Cumberbatch,
Evangeline Lilly, Lee Pace, Luke Evans, Ken Stott, James Nesbitt, and Orlando Bloom.
The films were shot simultaneously in 3D at a projection rate of 48 frames per second, with
principal photography taking place around New Zealand and at Pinewood Studios.
Additional filming took place throughout May 2013.
The Desolation of Smaug premiered in Los Angeles on 2 December 2013, and was released
on 12 December in New Zealand and on 13 December in the United States.
Produced by Warner Bros Pictures through its subsidiary New Line Cinema,  the film received mostly positive reviews and
grossed $959 million at the worldwide box office, making it the fourth highest-grossing film of 2013.
The film received numerous accolades; at the 86th Academy Awards, it was nominated
for Best Sound Editing, Best Sound Mixing, and Best Visual Effects.
The final instalment of the trilogy, The Hobbit: The Battle
of the Five Armies, was released in 2014.
The film explores themes of gold, lake, based on novel or book, elves, dwarf.